我们思考如何判断规格的下一个维度
Our next dimension for thinking about how we judge specs
是声明性的还是操作性的。
is declarative versus operational.
操作规范给出了一系列步骤
Operational specifications give a series of steps
方法执行的。
that the method performs.
所以伪代码描述将是一个操作规范。
So a pseudo code description would be an operational spec.
声明性规范不提供详细信息
Declarative specifications don't give details
中间步骤。
of those intermediate steps.
相反，它们只是描述了最终结果的性质
Instead, they just describe properties of the final outcome
最终输出状态的。
of the final output state.
以及它与初始状态，输入的关系。
And how that's related to the initial state, the inputs.
现在几乎总是，声明性规范更可取。
Now almost always, declarative specifications are preferable.
它们通常较短。
They're usually shorter.
他们通常更容易让客户理解。
They're usually easier for the client to understand.
最重要的是，它们不公开实现细节
And most importantly, they don't expose implementation details
客户机可能会对
that the client might develop a dependency on and then find
当实现发生更改时不再保持。
no longer hold when the implementation has changed.
例如，如果我们想
So for example, if we want to allow either
我们的find，find first和find last的实现，
of our implementations of find, find first and find last,
我们不想在说明书上说什么
we would not want to say in the spec something
就像方法在数组中向下移动直到
like the method goes down the array until it
找到[？元音？].
finds [? vowel ?].
除了这一点很模糊之外，
Since aside from this being rather vague,
规范实际上表明搜索继续进行
the spec actually suggests that the search proceeds
从低到高的指数
from lower to higher indices and that the lowest
将被退回。
will be returned.
也许说明符并没有真正的意图。
Which perhaps specifier did not actually intend.
程序员有时会失误的一个原因
One reason programmers sometimes lapse
编写一个操作规范是
into writing an operational spec is
因为他们正在使用规范注释
because they're using the spec comment
解释维护程序员的实现
to explain the implementation for a maintenance programmer
在那之后谁会继续。
who's going to follow on after that.
别那么做。
Don't do that.
记住你有两个不同的听众。
Keep in mind that you have two different audiences.
你有客户程序，或者有人
You have a client program, or somebody
谁在调用您的方法，谁是维护者
who is calling your method, and a maintainer
谁将实际执行和维护
who is actually going to be implementing and maintaining
你的实现。
your implementation.
对于规范，规范实际上是为客户设计的
For the spec, the spec is really designed for the client
还有维修人员。
and the maintainer.
但是维护者，沟通
But the maintainer, to communicate
对于维护人员，您真正想使用的是
with the maintainer you really want to use just
方法体中的注释。
comments within the body of your method.
现在对于任何给定的规格，可能
Now for any given specs, there may
有很多方法可以很好地表达它。
be many ways to express it well declaratively.
下面是一些开始的例子。
Here are some examples of starts with.
例如，从可能开始
So for example, starts with might
假设只有当且仅当
say that it returns true if and only
如果存在一些字符串后缀，例如
if there exists some string suffix such
前缀加后缀与字符串相同。
that prefix plus suffix is the same as string.
如果只有
You might say that returns true if and only
如果有一个整数，如果你取第一个
if there's an integer i such that if you take the first i
字符串中的字符，您将得到一个字符串
characters from string, you're going to get a string that's
等于前缀。
equal to prefix.
可能会说些更像英语的话
Might even say something that's more like English
如果字符串中的第一个字符数为
that this is true if the first number of characters in string
等于前缀点长度相同
equal to prefix dot length are the same
作为字符和前缀。
as the characters and prefix.
否则就错了。
Otherwise false.
这三个都是声明性规范
All three of these are declarative specifications
因为他们只是描述了返回值之间的关系
because they just described how the return value relates
输入值。
to the input value.
我们真的要选择清楚的规格
It's really up to us to choose the clear specifications
我们可以为[听不见]的客户和维护者提供服务。
that we can for the clients and maintainers of [INAUDIBLE].